Writing biography is a strange thing to do.
كتابة السيرة الذاتية أمر عجيب تقوم به
It's a journey into the foreign territory
إنها رحلة في أرض غريبة
of somebody else's life,
لحياة شخصا آخر
a journey, an exploration that can take you places
رحلة، اكتشاف يأخذك إلى أماكن
you never dreamed of going
لم تحلم بالذهاب إليها
and still can't quite believe you've been,
وتظل غير مصدق أنك كنت هناك
especially if, like me, you're an agnostic Jew
وخصوصا إذا، كنت مثلي، يهودية ﻻأدرًية
and the life you've been exploring
والحياة التي تستكشفها
is that of Muhammad.
هي حياة محمد.
Five years ago, for instance,
منذ خمس سنوات مضت، مثلا
I found myself waking each morning in misty Seattle
وجدت نفسي أستيقظ كل صباح في سياتل الضبابية
to what I knew was an impossible question:
على ذلك السؤال المستحيل
What actually happened
ما الذي حدث بالضبط
one desert night,
في ليلة صحراوية،
half the world and almost half of history away?
في منتصف العالم وتقريبا في منتصف التاريخ؟
What happened, that is,
ما الذي حدث، هناك،
on the night in the year 610
في تلك الليلة من عام 610
when Muhammad received the first revelation of the Koran
حين تلقى محمد أول الوحي من القرآن
on a mountain just outside Mecca?
على جبل خارج مكة؟
This is the core mystical moment of Islam,
إنها اللحظة الأساسية في اﻹسلام،
and as such, of course,
وﻷنها كذلك، بالطبع،
it defies empirical analysis.
فهي تتحدى التحليل العملي
Yet the question wouldn't let go of me.
لكن السؤال رفض أن يغادر تفكيري.
I was fully aware that for someone as secular as I am,
كنت مدركة تماما أن شخصا علمانيا مثلي،
just asking it could be seen
السؤال فقط يمكن أن ينظر إليه
as pure chutzpah.
على أنه نوع من الهرطقة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I plead guilty as charged,
وأنا أقر وأعترف بتهمتي،
because all exploration, physical or intellectual,
ﻷن الاستكشاف، سواء فعلي أو دراسي،
is inevitably in some sense an act of transgression,
هو حتما في سياق ما نوع من التعدي،
of crossing boundaries.
من تخطي الحدود.
Still, some boundaries are larger than others.
ومع ذلك، بعض الحدود أكبر من غيرها.
So a human encountering the divine,
لذلك حين يقابل إنسان الإله،
as Muslims believe Muhammad did,
كما يؤمن المسلمون أن محمد فعل،
to the rationalist, this is a matter not of fact
بالنسبة لمعتنقي العقلانية، هذا الأمر ليس حقيقي
but of wishful fiction,
بل أمنية خيالية،
and like all of us, I like to think of myself as rational.
ومثل الجميع، أحب أن أفكر أنني عقلانية.
Which might be why when I looked at the earliest accounts
ويبدو أن هذا هو السبب حين نظرت إلى التسجيلات القديمة
we have of that night,
حول تلك الليلة،
what struck me even more than what happened
الذي صعقني أكثر من الحادثة نفسها
was what did not happen.
هو الذي لم يحدث.
Muhammad did not come floating off the mountain
لم يطفوا محمد من على الجبل
as though walking on air.
كأنه يمشي في الهواء.
He did not run down shouting, "Hallelujah!"
لم يركض صارخا "الحمد لله!"
He did not radiate light and joy.
هو لم يشع نورا و فرحا
There were no choirs of angels,
لم تكن هناك جوقات من الملائكة،
no music of the spheres, no elation, no ecstasy,
ﻻ موسيقى في الأجواء، لا غبطة، لا نشوة،
no golden aura surrounding him,
لا هالة ذهبية محيطة به،
no sense of an absolute, fore-ordained role
لا أي إحساس مطلق، بالصدارة والترسيم المحتوم
as the messenger of God.
كرسول الله.
That is, he did none of the things
إنه، لم يفعل أي من اﻷشياء
that might make it easy to cry foul,
التي قد تسهل الحكم عليه بالافتراء،
to put down the whole story as a pious fable.
ﻹنهاء الحكاية كلها بوصفه مدعي التقوى واﻷساطير
Quite the contrary.
على العكس تماما.
In his own reported words,
حسبما قال وسُجل عنه،
he was convinced at first
كان مقتنعا في البداية
that what had happened couldn't have been real.
أن ما حدث يستحيل تصديقه.
At best, he thought, it had to have been a hallucination --
في أحسن اﻷحوال، اعتقد إنها هلوسة--
a trick of the eye or the ear, perhaps,
خدعه بصره أو سمعه، ربما
or his own mind working against him.
أو ربما انقلب عقله عليه.
At worst, possession --
في أسوأ اﻷحوال، تلبس--
that he'd been seized by an evil jinn,
استملك جسده من جان شرير،
a spirit out to deceive him,
روح هائمة تحاول خداعه،
even to crush the life out of him.
أو لعلها تحاول إزهاق روحه.
In fact, he was so sure that he could only be majnun,
في الواقع، اعتقد أن به مسا من الجنون،
possessed by a jinn,
تملكه جني ما،
that when he found himself still alive,
حتى أنه حين أدرك أنه لا يزال حيا،
his first impulse was to finish the job himself,
كانت أول ردة فعل له إتمام ذلك بنفسه،
to leap off the highest cliff
بأن يقفز عن أعلى منحدر
and escape the terror of what he'd experienced
ليهرب من الرعب الذي أصابه
by putting an end to all experience.
بوضع حد لكل المصائب.
So the man who fled down the mountain that night
لذلك فالرجل الذي نزل هاربا من الجبل في تلك الليلة
trembled not with joy
مرتعشا ﻻ من الفرحة
but with a stark, primordial fear.
بل بصرخة، يملأها الخوف.
He was overwhelmed not with conviction, but by doubt.
لم يطغى عليه الاقتناع، بل الشك.
And that panicked disorientation,
وذلك التوهان والرعب،
that sundering of everything familiar,
ذلك الانفصام عن كل معلوم،
that daunting awareness of something
ذلك اﻹدراك المروع لشيء
beyond human comprehension,
يتخطى إدراك البشر،
can only be called a terrible awe.
ﻻ يوصف إﻻ بالهلع الفظيع.
This might be somewhat difficult to grasp
لربما يكون من الصعب استيعاب هذه الكلمة
now that we use the word "awesome"
ﻷننا نستخدم كلمة "فظيع"
to describe a new app or a viral video.
لوصف تطبيق جديد أو فيديو منتشر.
With the exception perhaps of a massive earthquake,
مع الاستثناء ربما لوصف هزة أرضية ضخمة،
we're protected from real awe.
نحن محميون من الفظيع الحقيقي.
We close the doors and hunker down,
نحن نغلق على أنفسنا اﻷبواب ونحتمي،
convinced that we're in control,
مقتنعين أننا مسيطرون،
or, at least, hoping for control.
أو على اﻷقل، نأمل بالسيطرة.
We do our best to ignore the fact that
نفعل ما بوسعنا لنتجاهل الحقيقة
we don't always have it,
أننا لا نمتلكها دائما،
and that not everything can be explained.
وأننا ﻻ نستطيع تفسير كل شيء.
Yet whether you're a rationalist or a mystic,
بالرغم من ذلك سواء كنت عقلانيا أم روحانيا،
whether you think the words Muhammad heard that night
سواء اعتقدت أن الكلمات التي سمعها محمد في تلك الليلة
came from inside himself or from outside,
جاءت من داخل نفسه أو من خارجها،
what's clear is that he did experience them,
الواضح أنه حقا مر بتلك التجربة،
and that he did so with a force that would shatter
أن ما مر به كان من الشدة ليحطم
his sense of himself and his world
إحساسه بنفسه وبعالمه
and transform this otherwise modest man
وحولت ذلك الرجل المتواضع
into a radical advocate for social and economic justice.
إلى داعية راديكالي للعدالة الاجتماعية والاقتصادية.
Fear was the only sane response,
الخوف كان ردة الفعل العقلانية الوحيدة،
the only human response.
ردة الفعل اﻹنسانية الوحيدة.
Too human for some,
إنسانية كثيرا عند البعض،
like conservative Muslim theologians who maintain that
مثل قول علماء المسلمين المتحفظين
the account of his wanting to kill himself
أن القول بخاطرة الانتحار
shouldn't even be mentioned, despite the fact
يجب ذكرها، بالرغم من حقيقة
that it's in the earliest Islamic biographies.
وجودها في كتب السيرة اﻹسلامية القديمة.
They insist that he never doubted
يصرون على أنه لم يشك قط
for even a single moment, let alone despaired.
ولو للحظة واحدة، فما بالك باليأس.
Demanding perfection, they refuse to tolerate
بطلبهم الكمال، يرفضون التهاون مع
human imperfection.
النقص البشري.
Yet what, exactly, is imperfect about doubt?
لكن ما هو، بالضبط، النقص الموجود في الشك؟
As I read those early accounts, I realized it was
بينما كنت أقرأ تلك التسجيلات القديمة، أدركت أن
precisely Muhammad's doubt that brought him alive for me,
شك محمد ذاته هو الذي جعله حقيقيا بالنسبة لي،
that allowed me to begin to see him in full,
هو الذي جعلني أراه بصورة كاملة،
to accord him the integrity of reality.
ﻷن أشهد له بسلامة واقعه.
And the more I thought about it,
وكلما فكرت فيها أكثر،
the more it made sense that he doubted,
زاد اتضاحا أنه فعلا شك،
because doubt is essential to faith.
ﻷن الشك ضروري للإيمان.
If this seems a startling idea at first,
إذا بدت لكم كفكرة مروعة في البداية،
consider that doubt, as Graham Greene once put it,
خذوا في اعتباركم أن الشك، كما وصفه غراهام جرين،
is the heart of the matter.
هو جوهر المسألة.
Abolish all doubt, and what's left is not faith,
انزع كل الشك، وما يتبقى ليس اﻹيمان،
but absolute, heartless conviction.
بل اقتناع مطلق، بلا قلب.
You're certain that you possess the Truth --
أنت مقتنع أنك تمتلك الحقيقة--
inevitably offered with an implied uppercase T --
حتمية معطاة بال التعريف--
and this certainty quickly devolves
وهذه الحتمية بسرعة تؤول
into dogmatism and righteousness,
إلى دغمائية وصلاح،
by which I mean a demonstrative, overweening pride
أعني بذلك برهانية، بغرور وتعالي
in being so very right,
في كونهم على حق،
in short, the arrogance of fundamentalism.
باختصار، غطرسة اﻷصولية.
It has to be one of the multiple ironies of history
ﻻبد أنها أحد سخريات التاريخ المتعددة
that a favorite expletive of Muslim fundamentalists
أن الكلمة المفضلة عند اﻷصوليين من المسلمين
is the same one once used by the Christian fundamentalists
هي نفسها التي استخدمها اﻷصوليون من النصارى
known as Crusaders:
المعروفين بالصليبيين:
"infidel," from the Latin for "faithless."
"كافر" من اللاتينية بمعنى "عديم اﻹيمان".
Doubly ironic, in this case, because their absolutism
والسخرية مضاعفة، في هذه الحالة، أن حكمهم المطلق
is in fact the opposite of faith.
هو في الحقيقة عكس اﻹيمان.
In effect, they are the infidels.
في الواقع، هم الكفرة.
Like fundamentalists of all religious stripes,
مثل الأصوليين من جميع الشرائح الدينية،
they have no questions, only answers.
ﻻ تساؤلات لديهم، فقط إجابات.
They found the perfect antidote to thought
عثروا على المضاد اﻷمثل للفكر
and the ideal refuge of the hard demands of real faith.
والملجأ اﻷمثل للمطلب اﻷصعب للايمان الحقيقي.
They don't have to struggle for it like Jacob
لن يضطروا للصراع في سبيله مثل يعقوب
wrestling through the night with the angel,
منازعا الملائكة طوال الليل،
or like Jesus in his 40 days and nights in the wilderness,
أو مثل عيسى في أربعين يوما وليلة في البراري،
or like Muhammad, not only that night on the mountain,
أو مثل محمد، لم يقتصر اﻷمر على تلك الليلة على الجبل،
but throughout his years as a prophet,
بل طوال سنيه كرسول،
with the Koran constantly urging him not to despair,
والقرآن يحثه دوما أن ﻻ ييأس،
and condemning those who most loudly proclaim
ويدين أولئك الذين يعلنونها صراحة
that they know everything there is to know
أنهم يعلمون كل شيء
and that they and they alone are right.
وأنهم وحدهم هم فقط على الحق.
And yet we, the vast and still far too silent majority,
ولكننا نحن، الغالبية الشاسعة الصامتة،
have ceded the public arena to this extremist minority.
تنازلنا عن الساحة العامة للأصوليين القلة.
We've allowed Judaism to be claimed
سمحنا لليهودية أن يستولى عليها
by violently messianic West Bank settlers,
من قبل العنيفين من يهود المستوطنين في الضفة الغربية،
Christianity by homophobic hypocrites
النصرانية من قبل متخوفي المثلية المنافقين
and misogynistic bigots,
وكارهي النساء من المتعصبين،
Islam by suicide bombers.
اﻹسلام من قبل الانتحاريين.
And we've allowed ourselves to be blinded to the fact that
وسمحنا ﻷنفسنا أن نعمى عن حقيقة أنهم
no matter whether they claim to be Christians,
بغض النظر عن ادعاءهم أنهم نصارى،
Jews or Muslims,
أو يهود أو مسلمين،
militant extremists are none of the above.
ميلشيات اﻷصوليين لا تنتمي ﻷي مما سبق.
They're a cult all their own, blood brothers
إنهم ثقافة قائمة بذاتها، إخوة في الدم
steeped in other people's blood.
غارقين في دماء غيرهم من الناس.
This isn't faith.
هذا ليس باﻹيمان.
It's fanaticism, and we have to stop confusing the two.
إنه التعصب، ويجب علينا التوقف عن الخلط بينهما.
We have to recognize that real faith has no easy answers.
يجب علينا أن ندرك أن اﻹيمان الحقيقي ﻻ توجد له إجابات سهلة.
It's difficult and stubborn.
إنه صعب و عنيد.
It involves an ongoing struggle,
وهو يتضمن صراعا دائما،
a continual questioning of what we think we know,
تساؤﻻ دائما لما نعتقد أننا نعلمه،
a wrestling with issues and ideas.
تصارعا مع المسائل واﻷفكار.
It goes hand in hand with doubt,
وهو يمضي يدا بيد مع الشك،
in a never-ending conversation with it,
في حوار ﻻ ينتهي معه،
and sometimes in conscious defiance of it.
وأحيانا في تحد واع له.
And this conscious defiance is why I, as an agnostic,
وهذا التحدي الواعي هو السبب أنني، كلاأدرّية
can still have faith.
ﻻ يزال عندي إيمان.
I have faith, for instance, that peace in the Middle East
عندي إيمان، مثلا، أن السلام في الشرق اﻷوسط
is possible despite the ever-accumulating mass of evidence
ممكن على الرغم من الدﻻئل المتراكمة
to the contrary.
بعكس ذلك.
I'm not convinced of this.
لست مقتنعة بهذا.
I can hardly say I believe it.
بالكاد أقول أني أعتقد به.
I can only have faith in it,
يمكنني فقط أن أؤمن به،
commit myself, that is, to the idea of it,
ألزم نفسي، لفكرته،
and I do this precisely because of the temptation
وأنا أقوم بهذا تحديدا بسبب اﻹغراء
to throw up my hands in resignation
في رفع يدي في استسلام
and retreat into silence.
والتراجع في صمت.
Because despair is self-fulfilling.
ﻷن في اليأس أنانية.
If we call something impossible,
إذا سميناه مستحيلا،
we act in such a way that we make it so.
سنعمل بطريقة ما لنجعله كذلك.
And I, for one, refuse to live that way.
وأنا، عن نفسي، أرفض أن أعيش بهذه الطريقة.
In fact, most of us do,
في الحقيقة، معظمنا كذلك،
whether we're atheist or theist
سواء كنا ملاحدة أو مؤمنين
or anywhere in between or beyond, for that matter,
أو بين البينين في ذلك أو أبعد، لهذه المسألة،
what drives us is that, despite our doubts
ما يقودنا هو، بالرغم من شكوكنا
and even because of our doubts,
أو حتى بسبب شكوكنا،
we reject the nihilism of despair.
نحن نرفض عدمية اليأس.
We insist on faith in the future
نصر على اﻹيمان بالمستقبل
and in each other.
وفي بعضنا البعض.
Call this naive if you like.
سمها سذاجة إذا أحببت.
Call it impossibly idealistic if you must.
سمها مثالية مستحيلة إذا تحتم عليك.
But one thing is sure:
ولكن مؤكدا:
Call it human.
سمها إنسانية.
Could Muhammad have so radically changed his world
هل كان باستطاعة محمد تغيير عالمه جذريا
without such faith, without the refusal
بدون هذا اﻹيمان، بدون رفضه
to cede to the arrogance of closed-minded certainty?
التنازل لعجرفة عديمي البصيرة الحتميين؟
I think not.
ﻻ أعتقد ذلك.
After keeping company with him as a writer
بعد مصاحبتي له ككاتبة
for the past five years, I can't see
على مدى السنوات الخمس الماضية،ﻻ أراه
that he'd be anything but utterly outraged
إﻻ غاضبا كليا
at the militant fundamentalists who claim to speak
على ميلشيات اﻷصوليين الذين يدعون التحدث
and act in his name in the Middle East and elsewhere today.
والعمل باسمه في الشرق اﻷوسط وأي مكان اليوم.
He'd be appalled at the repression of half the population
سوف يشعر بالفزع من اضطهاد نصف السكان
because of their gender.
بسبب جنسهم.
He'd be torn apart by the bitter divisiveness of sectarianism.
سوف يتمزق من الانقسام الطائفي المر.
He'd call out terrorism for what it is,
سيسمي اﻹرهاب بما يستحق تسميته،
not only criminal but an obscene travesty
ليس إجراما فحسب بل مهزلة فاحشة
of everything he believed in and struggled for.
.لكل ما آمن وعانى من أجله.
He'd say what the Koran says: Anyone who takes a life
سوف ينادي بما قاله القرآن: من قتل نفسا بغير نفس
takes the life of all humanity.
أو فساد في الأرض فكأنما قتل الناس جميعا
Anyone who saves a life, saves the life of all humanity.
ومن أحياها فكأنما أحيا الناس جميعا
And he'd commit himself fully
وسوف يلزم نفسه كلية
to the hard and thorny process of making peace.
لعمل السلام الصعب والشائك.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)